So far we've been talking about
ここまでの所、我らはSVMについて
SVMs in a fairly abstract level.
かなり抽象的なレベルで議論してきた。
In this video I'd like to
このビデオでは、
talk about what you actually need
SVMを実際に走らせるにあたり、あるいは使うにあたり
to do in order to run or to use an SVM.
実際にやらなくてはいけない事について議論したい。
The support vector machine algorithm
サポートベクタマシンアルゴリズムは
poses a particular optimization problem.
特定の最適化問題を導く。
But as I briefly mentioned in
だが以前のビデオで
an earlier video, I really
簡単に述べた通り、
do not recommend writing your
パラメータシータを解くソフトウェアを
own software to solve for the parameter's theta yourself.
自力で書く事は、全く推奨しない。
So just as today, very
こんにちでは、
few of us, or maybe almost essentially
我々の中には、
none of us would think of
自分で行列の逆行列を求めるコードや
writing code ourselves to invert a matrix
数のルートを計算するコードを書こう、とする人は
or take a square root of a number, and so on.
かなり少数派、いやほとんど居ないと言っても良かろう。
We just, you know, call some library function to do that.
我らは、これを行うライブラリ関数を呼ぶ。
In the same way, the
同様に、
software for solving the SVM
SVMの最適化問題を
optimization problem is very
解くソフトウェアは、
complex, and there have
とても複雑だ。
been researchers that have been
そして、本質的には数値計算の最適化だけを何年もやってるような
doing essentially numerical optimization research for many years.
研究者達、というのも存在している。
So you come up with good
だから、あなたはこれを行ってくれる
software libraries and good software
素晴らしいソフトウェアライブラリや
packages to do this.
ソフトウェアパッケージを見つける事が出来る。
And then strongly recommend just using
であるから、自分で実装しよう、なんて考えないで
one of the highly optimized software
それらの高度に最適化されたソフトウェアライブラリのどれかを使う事を
libraries rather than trying to implement something yourself.
強く推奨する。
And there are lots of good software libraries out there.
良いソフトウェアライブラリは、たくさんあるから。
The two that I happen to
私がもっとも良く使う物を
use the most often are the
二つ上げておくと、
linear SVM but there are really
liblinearとlibsvmだが、
lots of good software libraries for
これを行うソフトウェアライブラリは
doing this that you know, you can
これ以外にもたくさんあって、
link to many of the
あなたが学習アルゴリズムを実装している言語に
major programming languages that you
リンク出来る物も
may be using to code up learning algorithm.
たくさんあるはずだ。
Even though you shouldn't be writing
あなたはSVMの最適化ソフトウェアを
your own SVM optimization software,
独自実装すべきでは無いのだけれども、
there are a few things you need to do, though.
あたながやるべき事も、ちょっとは存在する。
First is to come up
まず最初に、パラメータCを
with with some choice of the
選ばなくてはいけない。
parameter's C. We talked a
この事については
little bit of the bias/variance properties of
前回のビデオの中で、
this in the earlier video.
バイアス/バリアンス の性質の話の時に言及した。
Second, you also need to
二番目に、あなたが使うカーネル、あるいは
choose the kernel or the
類似度関数を
similarity function that you want to use.
選ぶ必要がある。
So one choice might
選択の一例としては、
be if we decide not to use any kernel.
カーネルを使わない、という決断もあり得る。
And the idea of no kernel
そしてカーネルを使わない、というアイデアは
is also called a linear kernel.
線形（リニア）カーネルとも呼ばれる。
So if someone says, I use
だから、誰かが
an SVM with a linear kernel,
「俺はSVMをリニアカーネルで使うぜ」と言ったら、
what that means is you know, they use
それの意味する事は、
an SVM without using without
SVMを、カーネル無しで
using a kernel and it
使う、という事。
was a version of the SVM
そしてそれは、SVMを
that just uses theta transpose X, right,
単に シータ転置 x で使うというSVMのバージョンという事になる。
that predicts 1 theta 0
それは以下の時に1を予測する、
plus theta 1 X1
シータ0+シータ1 x1
plus so on plus theta
足す、、、、っと足すことの シータn xn が、
N, X N is greater than equals 0.
0以上の時。
This term linear kernel, you
この「線形」カーネルという言葉は、
can think of this as you know this
これは標準的な「線形」の分類器を
is the version of the SVM
与えるSVMのバージョンだ、
that just gives you a standard linear classifier.
と考える事が出来る。
So that would be one
さて、これはある種の問題には
reasonable choice for some problems,
リーズナブルな選択となる。
and you know, there would be many software
そして世の中には
libraries, like linear, was
たくさんのソフトウェアのライブラリ、
one example, out of many,
たくさんあるそんなソフトウェアライブラリの中の
one example of a software library
一つの例としては、liblinearのような物とかが挙げられるが、
that can train an SVM
とにかく、SVMをカーネル無しで、
without using a kernel, also
またの名を線形カーネルでトレーニング出来る
called a linear kernel.
ソフトウェアライブラリはたくさんある。
So, why would you want to do this?
では、何故これを使いたい、と思うのだろうか？
If you have a large number of
もしあなたが、大量のフィーチャーを持っていて、
features, if N is
つまりnが大きくて、
large, and M the
そしてm、
number of training examples is
トレーニング手本の数が、小さければ、
small, then you know
その時はつまり、
you have a huge number of
あなたは大量のフィーチャーを
features that if X, this is
持っているという事で、
an X is an Rn, Rn +1.
xはRnとかRn+1という事だ。
So if you have a
だから既にたくさんの
huge number of features already, with
フィーチャーがあって、
a small training set, you know, maybe you
トレーニングセットのサイズは小さい、
want to just fit a linear
この場合は単に線形の
decision boundary and not try
決定境界へのフィッティングを望むかもしれない。
to fit a very complicated nonlinear
そしてあまり複雑な非線型の関数にフィッティングしたいとは思わないだろう。
function, because might not have enough data.
何故なら、十分なデータが無いと、
And you might risk overfitting, if
オーバーフィッティングのリスクがあるからだ。
you're trying to fit a very complicated function
とても次数の高いフィーチャー空間上の
in a very high dimensional feature space,
とても複雑な関数にフィッティングしようとしていて、
but if your training set sample
しかもトレーニングセットのサイズが小さい時には。
is small. So this
だからこそ、この状況は
would be one reasonable setting where
カーネルを使わない、
you might decide to just
または同じ事だが線形カーネルと呼ばれる物を使う、という
not use a kernel, or
選択をするのが合理的となる
equivalents to use what's called a linear kernel.
状況だ。
A second choice for the kernel that
あなたが行いそうな二番目の選択肢は
you might make, is this Gaussian
このガウスカーネルだ。
kernel, and this is what we had previously.
これは以前に得た物だ。
And if you do this, then the
そしてもしあなたがこれを選ぶなら、
other choice you need to make
あなたが行わなくてはいけないさらなる選択としては、
is to choose this parameter sigma squared
パラメータであるシグマ二乗を選ぶ事だ。
when we also talk a little bit about the bias variance tradeoffs
これはバイアス-バリアンスのトレードオフの話でちょっと触れたが、
of how, if sigma squared is
シグマ二乗が大きければ、
large, then you tend
高バイアス、低バリアンスの傾向の
to have a higher bias, lower
分類器となり、
variance classifier, but if
逆にシグマ二乗が
sigma squared is small, then you
小さければ、
have a higher variance, lower bias classifier.
高バリアンス、低バイアスの傾向の分類器となる。
So when would you choose a Gaussian kernel?
では、どんな時にガウスカーネルを使う事になるだろう？
Well, if your omission
それはだね。あなたの元々の
of features X, I mean
フィーチャーxが、
Rn, and if N
Rnとして、
is small, and, ideally, you know,
nが小さい時、そして理想的には、
if n is large, right,
mが大きい時。
so that's if, you know, we have
つまり、例えば二次元の
say, a two-dimensional training set,
トレーニングセットだとして、
like the example I drew earlier.
これは以前に書いた物と同様という事だが、
So n is equal to 2, but we have a pretty large training set.
つまりn=2だとして、だがトレーニングセットの総数は多いという場合。
So, you know, I've drawn in a
つまり、かなりたくさんの
fairly large number of training examples,
トレーニング手本を描いた。
then maybe you want to use
するとその場合、
a kernel to fit a more
もっと複雑な非線形の決定境界にフィットするような
complex nonlinear decision boundary,
カーネルを使いたくなる場合がある。
and the Gaussian kernel would be a fine way to do this.
そしてガウスカーネルはこれを行う良い方法だ。
I'll say more towards the end
このビデオの最後の方で
of the video, a little bit
線形カーネルを使う場合はどういう時か
more about when you might choose a
ガウスカーネルを選ぶのはどういう場合か、
linear kernel, a Gaussian kernel and so on.
などについて、話す機会がある。
But if concretely, if you
だが、もし具体的に
decide to use a Gaussian
ガウスカーネルを使う、と決めたとすると、
kernel, then here's what you need to do.
あなたがやるべき事はこれだ。
Depending on what support vector machine
あなたの使うサポートベクタマシンの
software package you use, it
ソフトウェアパッケージによっては、
may ask you to implement a
カーネル関数を、あるいは類似度関数を
kernel function, or to implement
あなたが実装する必要が
the similarity function.
あるものもある。
So if you're using an
もしあなたがoctaveやMATLABの
octave or MATLAB implementation of
SVMの実装を用いるなら、
an SVM, it may ask you
カーネルの具体的なフィーチャーを
to provide a function to
計算する関数を
compute a particular feature of the kernel.
あなたが提供する必要があるかもしれない。
So this is really computing f
これは本当は、
subscript i for one
fの下付き添字iを
particular value of i, where
ある特定の値に対して計算する、
f here is just a
ここでこのfは
single real number, so maybe
単一の実数値にすぎない、
I should move this better written
だからここでは、f(i)と書くべきかもしれない。
f(i), but what you
だがあなたがしなくてはいけない事は、
need to do is to write a kernel
これ、トレーニング手本やテスト手本や、
function that takes this input, you know,
とにかくなんであれ
a training example or a
あるベクトルxを
test example whatever it takes
入力として受け取り、
in some vector X and takes
そしてランドマークの一つを
as input one of the
入力として
landmarks and but
受け取るが、
only I've come down X1 and
ここでは私は単にこれらを
X2 here, because the
x1, x2と呼ぶ、
landmarks are really training examples as well.
何故ならランドマークも実際はトレーニング手本だから。
But what you
あなたがやらなくてはいけない事は、
need to do is write software that
この入力、x1とx2をうけとり
takes this input, you know, X1, X2
それらの間の、この種の類似度関数を
and computes this sort
計算して
of similarity function between them
一つの実数を返す
and return a real number.
ソフトウェアを書く事だ。
And so what some support vector machine
そこで幾つかのサポートベクタマシンのパッケージは
packages do is expect
あなたがこの種のカーネル関数、
you to provide this kernel function
x1とx2を入力に取って実数を返すような関数を
that take this input you know, X1, X2 and returns a real number.
提供する事を期待していて、
And then it will take it from there
そしてそこから、
and it will automatically generate all the features, and
自動的に全てのフィーチャーを生成して、
so automatically take X and
つまり自動的に、xに対し
map it to f1,
あなたの書いたこの関数を用いて
f2, down to f(m) using
f1, f2, ...とf(m)まで、
this function that you write, and
マッピングする。
generate all the features and
そして全てのフィーチャーを生成して、
train the support vector machine from there.
そこからサポートベクタマシンを訓練する。
But sometimes you do need to
だが、あなたは時々、
provide this function yourself.
この関数を自分で提供してやる必要がある。
Other if you are using the Gaussian kernel, some SVM implementations will also include the Gaussian kernel
ガウスカーネルを使う時でも、幾つかのSVM実装はガウスカーネルも含んでいて、
and a
そして
few other kernels as well, since
それ以外にも幾つかのカーネルを含んでいる物だ。
the Gaussian kernel is probably the most common kernel.
ガウスカーネルは恐らくもっとも一般的なカーネルなので、
Gaussian and linear kernels are
ガウスカーネルと線形カーネルは
really the two most popular kernels by far.
本当にぶっちぎりで大人気の二大カーネルなので、たぶんあるだろう。
Just one implementational note.
一つちょっとした実装のノートを。
If you have features of very
もしあなたのフィーチャーが、
different scales, it is important
とても異なるスケールだったら、
to perform feature scaling before
ガウスカーネルを使う前に
using the Gaussian kernel.
フィーチャースケーリングをするのが大切だ。
And here's why.
そして以下がその理由だ。
If you imagine the computing
あなたがxとlの間の
the norm between X and
ノルムを計算している所を、想像してみよう。
l, right, so this term here,
このここの項は、
and the numerator term over there.
こっちの分子の項だ。
What this is doing, the norm
これが行う事は、
between X and l, that's really
xとlの間のノルムで、
saying, you know, let's compute the vector
それは実際には、、、、ベクトルvを計算してみよう。
V, which is equal to
vはイコール x-lだとする。
X minus l. And then
そして次に、
let's compute the norm does
このベクトルvのノルムを計算する。
vector V, which is the
それはxとlとの間の
difference between X. So the
差だ。
norm of V is really
するとvのノルムは実際には
equal to V1 squared
イコール v1二乗、
plus V2 squared plus
足すことの v2二乗、
dot dot dot, plus Vn squared.
足すことの、点点点、足すことのvn二乗。
Because here X is in
ここでxはRn、
Rn, or Rn
いや、R n+1だが、
plus 1, but I'm going to ignore, you know, X0.
x0は無視する事にする。
So, let's pretend X is
そこでxはRnだとしよう、
an Rn, square on
左側を二乗すると
the left side is what makes this correct.
これは正しくなる。
So this is equal
そうすれば、これはイコール
to that, right?
こっちとなる。
And so written differently, this is
別の書き方で書くと、
going to be X1 minus l1
これはx1 - l(1)の二乗に、
squared, plus x2
足すことの x2-l(2)の二乗に、
minus l2 squared, plus
足すことの
dot dot dot plus Xn minus
点点点、、、と足すことの
ln squared.
xn - l(n)の二乗。
And now if your features
そして今、あなたのフィーチャーが
take on very different ranges of value.
とても異なったレンジの値を取るとしよう。
So take a housing
住宅の価格を予測する例で
prediction, for example, if
考えてみると、
your data is some data about houses.
データは住宅に関するデータで、
And if X is in the
ｘは、
range of thousands of square
最初のフィーチャーx1に関しては
feet, for the
何千平方フィートの範囲を
first feature, X1.
取り、
But if your second feature, X2 is the number of bedrooms.
しかし二番目のフィーチャーx2は寝室の数とすると、
So if this is in the
寝室の数は範囲としては
range of one to five bedrooms, then
1部屋から5部屋程度だろう、
X1 minus l1 is going to be huge.
するとx1-l(1)は巨大になりえて、
This could be like a thousand squared,
1000平方フィートとかに成り得るが、
whereas X2 minus l2
一方でx2-l(2)は
is going to be much smaller and if
もっと小さくなり、
that's the case, then in this term,
その場合には、この項、
those distances will be almost
これらの距離は、
essentially dominated by the
本質的にはほとんど住居のサイズで
sizes of the houses
支配されてしまい、
and the number of bathrooms would be largely ignored.
寝室の数はほとんど無視されてしまう。
As so as, to avoid this in
だから学習がうまくいくように
order to make a machine work
これを避ける為には、
well, do perform future scaling.
フィーチャースケーリングをせよ。
And that will sure that the SVM
そうする事で、SVMが
gives, you know, comparable amount of attention
様々なフィーチャーについて
to all of your different features,
同じような程度の関心を払うようにし、
and not just to in
この例の住居のサイズのように
this example to size of
他のフィーチャーを
houses were big movement here the features.
塗りつぶしてしまうような事が無い事を、保証出来る。
When you try a support vector
あなたがサポートベクタマシンを試みる時に、
machines chances are by
おそらくもっとも一般的であろう
far the two most common
二つのカーネルは、
kernels you use will
線形(linear)カーネル、つまり
be the linear kernel, meaning no
カーネル無しか、
kernel, or the Gaussian kernel that we talked about.
または既に話したガウスカーネルだろう。
And just one note of warning
そしてちょっと注意を。
which is that not all similarity
類似度関数ならば、
functions you might come up
どんな物でも
with are valid kernels.
カーネルとして使える、という訳では無い。
And the Gaussian kernel and the linear
そしてガウスカーネル、線形カーネル、
kernel and other kernels that you
そしてたまに他の人が使ってるのを見かける
sometimes others will use, all
その他のカーネルでも、
of them need to satisfy a technical condition.
それらはある技術的条件を満たす必要がある。
It's called Mercer's Theorem and
それはMercerの定理と言われる物だ。
the reason you need to this
これが必要となる理由は、
is because support vector machine
サポートベクタマシンのアルゴリズム、
algorithms or implementations of the
全てのSVMの実装は、
SVM have lots of clever
大量の賢い
numerical optimization tricks.
数値計算的な最適化のトリックを使ってる、
In order to solve for the
パラメータのシータについて
parameter's theta efficiently and
効率的に解く為に。
in the original design envisaged,
そしてオリジナルのSVMの設計において、
those are decision made to restrict
主な関心を、Mercerの定理と呼ばれる
our attention only to kernels
技術的条件を満たすカーネルだけに
that satisfy this technical condition called Mercer's Theorem.
集中する、という決定がなされた。
And what that does is, that
そうする事で、
makes sure that all of these
それらSVMパッケージの全てで、
SVM packages, all of these SVM
それら全てのSVMソフトウェアパッケージで
software packages can use the
大きなクラスの最適化を
large class of optimizations and
用いる事が出来るようになり、
get the parameter theta very quickly.
パラメータのシータをとても早く得られるようになる。
So, what most people end up doing
さて、結局の所、ほとんどの人が使うのは
is using either the linear
線形カーネルか
or Gaussian kernel, but there
ガウスカーネルだ。
are a few other kernels that also
だがそれ以外にも幾つか
satisfy Mercer's theorem and
Mercerの定理を満たすカーネルが存在する。
that you may run across other
そして他の人々がそれらを使ってる所を
people using, although I personally
あなたがみかける事もあるかもしれない。
end up using other kernels you know, very, very rarely, if at all.
私個人としては、それ以外のカーネルを使う事ってほんとにほんとーに稀で、全く無いって事は無いにせよほとんど無いけど。
Just to mention some of the other kernels that you may run across.
あなたが遭遇するかもしれない幾つかのカーネルをちょっとだけ言及しておくと、
One is the polynomial kernel.
一つ目は多項式カーネル。
And for that the similarity between
その場合、xとlの間の
X and l is
類似度は、
defined as, there are
どう定義されるかというと、
a lot of options, you can
たくさんの選択肢があるが、
take X transpose l squared.
xの転置 l の二乗という定義がありうる。
So, here's one measure of how similar X and l are.
これは、xとlがどれだけ類似してるかを測る、一つの指標である。
If X and l are very close with
xとlがお互いにとても近いと、
each other, then the inner product will tend to be large.
内積は大きくなる傾向にある。
And so, you know, this is a slightly
このカーネルは
unusual kernel.
ちょっと珍しいカーネルで、
That is not used that often, but
そんなには使われていない。
you may run across some people using it.
だがたまには、使ってる人に出くわす事もあるかもしれない。
This is one version of a polynomial kernel.
これは多項式カーネルの一つのバージョンだ。
Another is X transpose l cubed.
もう一つ別の物としては、x転置 l の三乗。
These are all examples of the polynomial kernel.
これらは全て、多項式カーネルの例だ。
X transpose l plus 1 cubed.
x転置 l + 1 の三乗、
X transpose l plus maybe
x転置 l 足すことの
a number different then one 5
1以外の数でも良い。5とか。
and, you know, to the power of 4 and
そして4乗。
so the polynomial kernel actually has two parameters.
つまり、多項式カーネルは実際には二つのパラメータがある。
One is, what number do you add over here?
一つはどの数をここに足すか？
It could be 0.
これは0でも良い。
This is really plus 0 over there, as well as what's the degree of the polynomial over there.
ここには実はプラス0がある。 同様に、ここの、多項式の次数(degree)がある。
So the degree power and these numbers.
つまり累乗の指数。そしてこれらの数字。
And the more general form of the
多項式カーネルの
polynomial kernel is X
より一般的な形としては、
transpose l, plus some
x転置 l 足すことの
constant and then
ある定数(const)
to some degree in the
そして指数のある次数(degree)。
X1 and so both
つまりこれら二つの両方が
of these are parameters for the polynomial kernel.
多項式カーネルのパラメータだ。
So the polynomial kernel almost always
多項式カーネルは、ほとんどいつでも
or usually performs worse.
ガウスカーネルよりも
And the Gaussian kernel does not
より劣ったパフォーマンスを示す。
use that much, but this is just something that you may run across.
だからそんなに使われない。でもたまに出くわす事がある物ではある。
Usually it is used only for
通常、これはxとlが
data where X and l
全て0より大きい、
are all strictly non negative,
非負のデータに対してのみ使われる。
and so that ensures that these
そうする事で、これらの内積が
inner products are never negative.
決して負にならない事を担保している。
And this captures the intuition that
そしてこれは、xとlがとてもお互いに近いと
X and l are very similar
それら同士の内積が大きくなるだろう、という
to each other, then maybe the inter product between them will be large.
直感を捕捉している。
They have some other properties as well
他の性質もあるんだが、
but people tend not to use it much.
何にせよ人々はあまり使ってない。
And then, depending on what you're
そしてさらに、あなたがやっている事に応じて、
doing, there are other, sort of more
ある種より難解なカーネルも
esoteric kernels as well, that you may come across.
存在して、あなたがそれらに遭遇する事もあるかもしれない。
You know, there's a string kernel, this
文字列カーネルというのがある、
is sometimes used if your
これはあなたの入力データがテキスト文字列なり、
input data is text strings or other types of strings.
それ以外でも文字列の時には、時々使われる事がある。
There are things like the
カイ二乗カーネルという物もあり、
chi-square kernel, the histogram intersection kernel, and so on.
ヒストグラム交差カーネルという物などもある。
There are sort of more esoteric kernels that
これらは異なるオブジェクト同士の
you can use to measure similarity
類似度を測る事が出来る
between different objects.
ある種より難解なカーネルだ。
So for example, if you're trying to
例えば、あなたがある種の
do some sort of text classification
テキスト分類の問題に挑んでいる時には、
problem, where the input
入力xが文字列となるので、
x is a string then
我らは二つの
maybe we want to find the
文字列の間の
similarity between two strings
類似度を、文字列カーネルを用いる事で
using the string kernel, but I
知りたいかもしれない。
personally you know end up very rarely,
だが私個人としては、これらのより難解なカーネルは
if at all, using these more esoteric kernels. I
全く見ないとは言わないが、とても稀にしか見ない。
think I might have use the chi-square
カイ2乗カーネルを、たぶん私は生涯で、
kernel, may be once in
一回しか使ったことが無いと思うし、
my life and the histogram kernel,
ヒストグラムカーネルは
may be once or twice in my life. I've
人生で一回か二回だったと思う。
actually never used the string kernel myself. But in
私は実は、文字列カーネルを自分で使った事は無い。
case you've run across this in other applications. You know, if
しかしもしあなたが別のアプリケーションでこれらに遭遇したら、
you do a quick web
ちょろっとwebを検索して、
search we do a quick Google
Googleで軽く検索するなり、
search or quick Bing search
Bingで軽く検索すれば、
you should have found definitions that these are the kernels as well. So
これらのカーネルの定義を見つける事が出来るはずだ。
just two last details I want to talk about in this video. One in multiclass classification. So, you
このビデオで話しておきたい細かい話が最後に二つ。 一つはマルチクラスの分類問題について。
have four classes or more generally
4つのクラスがあったとしよう、あるいはもっと一般的に
3 classes output some appropriate
k個のクラスの出力があったとしよう。 複数のクラス間の適切な決定境界を
decision bounday between your multiple classes. Most SVM, many SVM
SVMにどのように計算させたら良いだろうか？
packages already have built-in
ほとんどのSVM、とは言い過ぎだが多くのSVMパッケージは、既にマルチクラスの分類の機能が
multiclass classification functionality. So
ビルドインされている。
if your using a pattern like
だからもしあなたがそのようなパッケージを使っているなら、
that, you just use the
あなたは単に、ビルドインの機能を
both that functionality and that
使うだけで、
should work fine. Otherwise,
うまくいくはずだ。
one way to do this
そうで無ければ、これを行う方法の一つには、
is to use the one
1 vs allの手法を
versus all method that we
使う事だ、これについては
talked about when we are developing logistic regression. So
ロジスティック回帰を作ってる時に議論した。
what you do is you trade
あなたがやる事は、K個のSVMを
kSVM's if you have
トレーニングする、もしあなたがKクラス
k classes, one to distinguish
あったとしてだが、一度に一つのクラスを
each of the classes from the rest.
それ以外のクラスと区別するように。
And this would give you k parameter
そしてこれは、K個のパラメータベクトルを与える。
vectors, so this will
つまりこれは、あなたに
give you, upi lmpw. theta 1, which
パラメータベクトルのシータ1を与え、
is trying to distinguish class y equals
これはクラスy=1を
one from all of
それ以外のクラスから区別しようと
the other classes, then you
試みる物で、
get the second parameter, vector
そして次に二番目のパラメータベクトル、
theta 2, which is what
シータ2を与え、これは
you get when you, you know, have
y=2を陽性のクラスとした時に
y equals 2 as the positive class
そしてそれ以外全てを陰性のクラスとした時に
and all the others as negative class
得られるパラメータで、
and so on up to
そうやってパラメータベクトル
a parameter vector theta k,
シータKまで、
which is the parameter vector for
これは最後のクラスKを
distinguishing the final class
それ以外と区別する
key from anything else, and
パラメータベクトルだ。
then lastly, this is exactly
最後に、これはまさに
the same as the one versus
ロジスティック回帰でやった
all method we have for logistic regression.
1 vs ALL法だ。
Where we you just predict the class
そこではあなたは
i with the largest theta
シータ転置 xが最大になったクラスiを
transpose X.  So let's multiclass classification designate.
予想とするのだった。以上がマルチクラスの分類の方法だ。
For the more common cases
だがもっと一般的なケースとしては、
that there is a good
だいたいは、かなり良い確率で、
chance that whatever software package
あなたが何のソフトウェアパッケージを使ってるにせよ、
you use, you know, there will be
だいたいは、
a reasonable chance that are already
かなりの確率で、そこには
have built in multiclass classification functionality,
既にマルチクラスの機能がビルドインされている。
and so you don't need to worry about this result.
だからこの事について思い悩む必要は無い。
Finally, we developed support vector
最後に、我らはサポートベクタマシンを
machines starting off with logistic
ロジスティック回帰から始めて、
regression and then modifying the cost function a little bit.
コスト関数をちょっと変更していく事で開発してきた。
The last thing we want to do in this video is, just say a little bit about.
このビデオで最後にやりたい事は、これらの二つのアルゴリズムの
when you will use one of
どちらをいつ使うのか、について
these two algorithms, so let's
ちょっと話しておきたい。
say n is the number
nをフィーチャーの数として、
of features and m is the number of training examples.
mをトレーニング手本の数とする。
So, when should we use one algorithm versus the other?
さて、いつどちらのアルゴリズムを使い、いつもう一つのアルゴリズムを使うべきだろう？
Well, if n is larger
もしnがトレーニングセットサイズとの相対的に
relative to your training set
大きければ、
size, so for example,
例を挙げると、
if you take a business
フィーチャーの数が
with a number of features this is
これがmよりずっと
much larger than m and this
大きくて、
might be, for example, if you
そしてこれが、例えば、
have a text classification problem, where
テキスト分類の問題だとすると、
you know, the dimension of the feature
フィーチャーのベクトルの次元は、
vector is I don't know, maybe, 10 thousand.
知らんけど例えば1万とかになりがちで、
And if your training
そしてトレーニングセットのサイズが
set size is maybe 10
10から、
you know, maybe, up to 1000.
せいぜい1000くらいまでの間。
So, imagine a spam
スパム分類の問題を
classification problem, where email
想像してみよう。
spam, where you have 10,000
e-mailスパムでは、1万の単語に対応した
features corresponding to 10,000 words
1万個のフィーチャーがあるとする、
but you have, you know, maybe 10
でも例えば10通からせいぜい1000通とかの
training examples or maybe up to 1,000 examples.
トレーニング手本しか無いとする。
So if n is large relative to
つまり、nはmとの相対で考えると大きい。
m, then what I
その場合に私が普段やるのは、
would usually do is use logistic
ロジスティック回帰を使うか、
regression or use it
カーネル無しの、あるいは線形カーネルの
as the m without a kernel or
SVMを
use it with a linear kernel.
使う。
Because, if you have so many
何故なら、そんなにたくさんのフィーチャーで、
features with smaller training sets, you know,
トレーニングセットが小さいと、
a linear function will probably
線形関数はたぶんいい感じだと思う、
do fine, and you don't have
そしてとても複雑な非線形の関数を
really enough data to
フィッティングするには
fit a very complicated nonlinear function.
十分なデータを持ってない。
Now if is n is
今、もしnが小さくて、
small and m is
mが中くらいの大きさだと、
intermediate what I mean
ここでnとしては
by this is n is
1から1000くらいを
maybe anywhere from 1 - 1000, 1 would be very small.
イメージしてて、1はとても小さい場合だが、
But maybe up to 1000
せいぜい1000フィーチャーくらいまで、
features and if
そして
the number of training
トレーニング手本の総数が
examples is maybe anywhere from
10から1万手本くらいの間の
10, you know, 10 to maybe up to 10,000 examples.
どこか位。
Maybe up to 50,000 examples.
5万くらいまでの間でもいいかもしれない。
If m is pretty big like maybe 10,000 but not a million.
mがとても大きければ、1万くらい。だが100万は行かない。
Right? So if m is an
さて、mがもし
intermediate size then often
中くらいのサイズの時は、
an SVM with a linear kernel will work well.
しばしばSVMに線形カーネルが、うまく機能するだろう。
We talked about this early as
この場合については以前にも話した、
well, with the one concrete example,
一つの具体例で。
this would be if you have
それは、もしあなたが二次元の
a two dimensional training set. So, if n
トレーニングセットの時に、
is equal to 2 where you
つまり、もしn=2の時で、
have, you know, drawing in a pretty large number of training examples.
たくさんのトレーニング手本が描いてある時などは、
So Gaussian kernel will do
ガウスカーネルは、陽性と陰性のクラスを分離するのに
a pretty good job separating positive and negative classes.
きわめて良い働きをするだろう。
One third setting that's of
興味のある三番目の状況としては、
interest is if n is
nが小さくて
small but m is large.
mが大きい時。
So if n is you know, again maybe
例えばnは1から1000までとか、
1 to 1000, could be larger.
もうちょっと大きくてもいいかもしれないが、
But if m was, maybe
しかしmは5万くらいから
50,000 and greater to millions.
100とかまでとか、
So, 50,000, a 100,000, million, trillion.
5万から10万、100万、200万、と、
You have very very large training set sizes, right.
とても大きなトレーニングセットのサイズの時、
So if this is the case,
この場合は、
then a SVM of the
ガウスカーネルのSVMは
Gaussian Kernel will be somewhat slow to run.
走らせるといくらか遅い。
Today's SVM packages, if you're
こんにちのSVMパッケージでは、
using a Gaussian Kernel, tend to struggle a bit.
ガウスカーネルを使うと、
If you have, you know, maybe 50
5万くらいなら、
thousands okay, but if you
たぶん問題無い。
have a million training examples, maybe
だが、100万個のトレーニング手本だと、
or even a 100,000 with a
または10万個のトレーニング手本で、かつ
massive value of m. Today's
nが大きい値の時には、
SVM packages are very good,
こんにちのSVMパッケージはとても良い物だが、
but they can still struggle
それでも大量の、本当に大量の
a little bit when you have a
トレーニングセットの時には
massive, massive trainings that size when using a Gaussian Kernel.
ガウスカーネルを使うとちょっとだけ苦戦するかもしれない。
So in that case, what I
その場合には、
would usually do is try to just
私が普段やるのは、
manually create have more
手動でフィーチャーを増やして
features and then use
ロジスティック回帰を使うか、
logistic regression or an SVM
カーネル無しのSVMを
without the Kernel.
試す。
And in case you look at this
そしてもしあなたがこのスライドを見て
slide and you see logistic regression
ロジスティック回帰とカーネル無しのSVMが
or SVM without a kernel.
これらの場所がいつも
In both of these places, I
ペアで一緒に出てきてると
kind of paired them together. There's
思ったなら、
a reason for that, is that
それには理由があるのだ。
logistic regression and SVM without
ロジスティック回帰とカーネル無しのSVM、
the kernel, those are really pretty
これらは実際にはかなり
similar algorithms and, you know, either
似たアルゴリズムだ。
logistic regression or SVM
ロジスティック回帰もカーネル無しのSVMも
without a kernel will usually do
通常は極めて似た
pretty similar things and give
振る舞いをする。そして極めて似た
pretty similar performance, but depending
パフォーマンスを与える。
on your implementational details, one may be more efficient than the other.
だが実装の詳細によっては、片方がもう片方よりも効率的だったりはするかもしれない。
But, where one of
だが、これらのアルゴリズムの
these algorithms applies, logistic
一つを適用する時、
regression where SVM without a
ロジスティック回帰とカーネル無しのSVMの
kernel, the other one is to likely
どちらも、だいたい同様に
to work pretty well as well.
機能する。
But along with the power of
だがSVMの威力は、
the SVM is when you
複雑な非線型の関数を
use different kernels to learn
学習する為に
complex nonlinear functions.
別のカーネルを使う時に発揮される。
And this regime, you know, when you
そしてこの形態では、
have maybe up to 10,000 examples, maybe up to 50,000.
1万手本くらいまでとか、5万手本くらいまでとかで、
And your number of features,
そしてフィーチャーの数は、
this is reasonably large.
ちょうど良い程度に多い、
That's a very common regime
これはとても良くある形態だ。
and maybe that's a regime
そしてこの状況こそ、
where a support vector machine with a kernel kernel will shine.
カーネルと共にサポートベクタマシンを用いる事が、光り輝く形態だ。
You can do things that are much
ロジスティック回帰を使ってではもっと大変になるような事を
harder to do that will need logistic regression.
やる事が出来る。
And finally, where do neural networks fit in?
そして最後に、ニューラルネットワークが適合するのはどういう形態か？
Well for all of these
うーん、これら全ての問題に対して、
problems, for all of
これらの別々の形態
these different regimes, a well
全てに対して、
designed neural network is likely to work well as well.
良く設計されたニューラルネットワークは、うまく機能するだろう。
The one disadvantage, or the one
一つの欠点としては、あるいは
reason that might not sometimes use
ニューラルネットワークを使わない事がある
the neural network is that,
理由の一つには、
for some of these problems, the
これらの問題の中には、
neural network might be slow to train.
ニューラルネットワークは訓練するのに遅いという場合がある。
But if you have a very good
だがもしとても良い
SVM implementation package, that
SVM実装パッケージがあるなら、
could run faster, quite a bit faster than your neural network.
そちらの方が速く走りうる、ニューラルネットワークよりずっと速く走る。
And, although we didn't show this
そして、これは証明しなかったが、
earlier, it turns out that
SVMの持つ
the optimization problem that the
最適化の問題は、
SVM has is a convex
凸最適化問題である事が
optimization problem and so the
知られている。
good SVM optimization software
だから良いSVM最適化ソフトウェアパッケージは
packages will always find
必ずグローバル最小か、それに近い値を
the global minimum or something close to it.
探してくれる。
And so for the SVM you don't need to worry about local optima.
だからSVMでは、ローカル最適の問題を心配する必要は無い。
In practice local optima aren't
現実問題としては、ニューラルネットワークでも
a huge problem for neural networks
ローカル最適はそんなに大きな問題では無い。
but they all solve, so this
だけど、、、あー、
is one less thing to worry about if you're using an SVM.
とにかくSVMを使えば、心配事が一つ減ると言えば減る。
And depending on your problem, the neural
そして問題によっては、
network may be slower, especially
ニューラルネットワークの方が遅いかもしれない、
in this sort of regime than the SVM.
特にこの形態の問題では、SVMよりも遅いかもしれない。
In case the guidelines they gave
ここに示したガイドラインが
here, seem a little bit vague
ちょっと曖昧だなぁ、と思っても、
and if you're looking at some problems, you know,
もしあなたが何かの問題に際して、
the guidelines are a bit
ガイドラインがいまいち曖昧だなぁ、と思っても、
vague, I'm still not entirely
私もいまだに完全には確信が持てる訳では無い、
sure, should I use this
私はこっちのアルゴリズムを使うべきか？
algorithm or that algorithm, that's actually okay.
あるいはあっちのアルゴリズムを使うべきか。それは実際には問題無い。
When I face a machine learning
私が機械学習の問題に直面する時には、
problem, you know, sometimes its actually
時々、
just not clear whether that's the
どのアルゴリズムを使うのがベストなのか、
best algorithm to use, but as
はっきりしない事がある。
you saw in the earlier videos, really,
だが以前のビデオで見た通り、
you know, the algorithm does
アルゴリズムは確かに重要だけど、
matter, but what often matters
しかししばしばもっと重要なのは、
even more is things like, how much data do you have.
どれだけの量のデータを持ってるか、
And how skilled are you, how
そしてどれだけあなたの技術力が高いか、
good are you at doing error
エラー分析や学習アルゴリズムをデバッグするのを
analysis and debugging learning
どれだけうまく行えるか、
algorithms, figuring out how
新しいフィーチャーをどうデザインする方法を
to design new features and
どれだけうまく見いだせるか、
figuring out what other features to give you learning algorithms and so on.
学習アルゴリズムに渡す別のフィーチャーをどれだけ上手く見いだせるか、などだったりする。
And often those things will matter
そしてしばしば、これらの事項は
more than what you are
あなたがロジスティック回帰を使うかSVMを使うか、よりも
using logistic regression or an SVM.
もっと重要な事だろう。
But having said that,
だが、言ってきたように、
the SVM is still widely
SVMはいまだに、
perceived as one of
もっとも強力な学習アルゴリズムの一つだと
the most powerful learning algorithms, and
広く受け止められている。
there is this regime of when there's
そしてSVMが複雑な非線型の関数を
a very effective way to learn complex non linear functions.
とても良く学習出来るような事態がある。
And so I actually, together with
そして私も実際、、、
logistic regressions, neural networks, SVM's,
ロジスティック回帰、ニューラルネットワーク、SVM、
using those to speed
これら三つの学習アルゴリズムを
learning algorithms you're I think
使えるなら、私が思うにあなたは
very well positioned to build
とても広範な応用に対し
state of the art you know,
最先端の機械学習システムを
machine learning systems for a wide
構築するのに
region for applications and this
とても良い位置に居る。
is another very powerful tool to have in your arsenal.
そしてこれはもう一つ、あなたの武器庫に備えておくのに良い、とてもパワフルなツールという訳だ。
One that is used all
この一つは、シリコンバレー中で
over the place in Silicon Valley,
業界中で、
or in industry and in
アカデミックな世界で、
the Academia, to build many
多くの高パフォーマンスの機械学習システムを作るのに
high performance machine learning system.
使われている物だ。